<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>3 on Дмитрий Власов</title>
    <link>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication_types/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 3 on Дмитрий Власов</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>ru-ru</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication_types/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Глава 11. Синтаксический анализ JSON</title>
      <link>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication/fparsec-tutorial/11-parsing-json/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication/fparsec-tutorial/11-parsing-json/</guid>
      <description>Now that we have discussed the basics of FParsec we are well prepared to work through a real world parser example: a JSON parser.
JSON (JavaScript Object Notation) is a text-based data interchange format with a simple and lightweight syntax. You can find descriptions of the syntax on json.org and in RFC 4626.
In many applications one only has to deal with JSON files describing one particular kind of object. In such a context it sometimes can be appropriate to write a specialized parser just for that specific kind of JSON file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Глава 12. Куда дальше?</title>
      <link>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication/fparsec-tutorial/12-what-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication/fparsec-tutorial/12-what-now/</guid>
      <description>If this tutorial has whet your appetite for a more in-depth introduction to FParsec, just head over to the user&amp;rsquo;s guide. If you can&amp;rsquo;t wait to write your own parser, then bookmark the parser overview page, maybe take a short look at the example parsers in the Samples folder and just start hacking. You can always consult the user&amp;rsquo;s guide at a later point should you get stuck somewhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Учебник библиотеки FParsec</title>
      <link>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication/fparsec-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://DmitriyVlasov.ru/publication/fparsec-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Введение Этот учебник знакомит вас с основными понятиями библиотеки FParsec. Наша цель &amp;mdash; дать вам возможность попробовать создать приложения синтаксического разбора с помощью библиотеки FParsec. Мы охватим только основные идеи и дадим беглый обзор библиотеки по APIen. Но, надеемся, это будет достаточной основой для того, чтобы вы могли в дальнейшем использовать FParsec самостоятельно с помощью: руководства пользователяen, справочника по APIen и примеров синтаксических анализаторов в папке Samplesen.
Благодарности Благодарю мою жену Ольгу за помощь в переводе, стилистической выверке и редактуре теста.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>